A Guide to the Otti Y. Windmueller Papers, 1951-1994
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Otti Y. Windmueller papers 1951-1994
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 424
1 Linear Feet (3 boxes).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Steven Windmueller, son of Otti Y. Windmueller, 2002
Biographical Information
Otti Y. Herman Windmueller was born in Borghorst, Germany August 16, 1916 to an upper middle class Jewish family. After graduating high school, Nazi law dictated that as a Jewish woman she could receive no further education. Windmueller was determined, and found a non-Jewish yet sympathetic dress maker to take her on as an apprentice. She completed her three year apprenticeship and rose to assistant designer by 1938. Her older brother, Wilhelm, had just relocated to Johannesburg, South Africa and Otti was eager to follow him. When Fred Windmueller proposed to her she said yes on the condition they follow her brother. Fred already had family in Richmond, Virginia with visas to arrive in the United States. The border to South Africa closed and made their decision for them. In 1938, the newlyweds, knowing each other for less than two months, boarded the S.S. Volendam. Krystalnacht was six months later. Otti's two sisters escaped to England, and later moved to America. Their parents were murdered in concentration camps. She reunited with her family and made the oral history based on family interviews in 1991 which can be found at the Jacob Radar Marcus Center of Jewish American Archives, part of the Cincinnati campus of Hebrew Union College-Jewish Institute of Religion. Her husband Fred, who was the Temple Archivist for Beth Ahaba in Richmond, originated the Windmueller Family Chronicle which also documents their departure from Germany.
Once in Richmond, Otti found what work she could as a seamstress while attending Richmond Professional Institute. She earned a BA in Fine Arts. In 1953 she became a part-time instructor in the Fashion Department. Thus began her forty year career at RPI then VCU in the Fashion Department. She was known for bringing her European flair to the design, set up several study abroad trips for the students, brought couture designers to VCU to lecture and contributed her in depth knowledge of pattern making. She was the Chair of the department from 1965 to 1976, after which she stepped down to teach full time again. In 1993 she was named Professor Emerita and established the Otti Y. Windmueller Scholarship. After her retirement she continued her involvement with the university through volunteer work with VCU and MCV. Otti Y. Windmueller died December 12, 2001.
Scope and Content
This collection chronicles some of Otti Y. Windmueller's accomplishments at VCU's Department of Fashion as well as personal correspondence with friends and family and the story of her survival as young Jewish Woman in Nazi Germany as portrayed in the articles about and interviews with Windmueller, spanning from 1951 to 1994 with the majority of materials dating from the 1980s and early 1990s.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically, with exception to oversize, and is comprised of three series: 1. Correspondence and Documents, 1951-1994, 2. Photographs, 1980s-1994, 3. News clippings, 1980s-1990s.
Contents List
- Correspondence and documents 1951-1994 (Box 1)
  - Arts in the Hospital, undated (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Bar Mitzvah & Bat Torah Invitations, 1980s (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Beth Ahabah, in regards to Morris Perlstein, 1976 August 8, 1984 December 26, 1985 February 7 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Black-Schaffers, undated (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Brown, David, undated (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Cassel, Gunter and Rita, also known as Loompies, 1989 January 29 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Hatfield, Judith, in regards to Elderhostel 1988 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Heimatverin, Borghorst, Vositzender, 1995 March 5 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Hintz, Dolly, 1981, 1984 April 26, 1986 January 23 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Hirschberg, Ruth, includes Chronicle to Rabbi Hirschberg, 1990 January 29 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Hoffman, Alfred, 1963 November 21, 1966 December 20, 1986 September 6, 1986 September 17, 1987 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Inge and Harold, Niece and Nephew in-law, 1986, September 22, 1994, undated (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Karp, Pearl with the Jewish Community Center, 1991 December 25 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Kleibacker, Charles, 1991 August (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Kruger, Morris, 1988 March 3 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Lewis, Sydney, 1986 July 8, 1987 June 24, 1988 August 15, 1990 April 13 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - MCV Volunteers, 1988 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Neal, Gail, circa 1980s (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Obrochta, William with the Virginia Historical Society, 1992 January 15 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Rizzo, Frank, undated (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Rubin, Saul, Rabbi, 1971 August 12 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Sara, Dorthea, Handwriting Analyst, 1959 April 7 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Snyder, Debbie, 1986 July 16 (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Spiro, Jack, Rabbi, 1974 May 20, 1994 May 20 (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Stern, Toni, Sister, 1989 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Thalhimer, Charles G., 1990 May 22 (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Town and Country Realty, 1968 September 26 (Box-folder 1:27)
  - Valentine Museum, 1983 August 18 (Box-folder 1:28)
  - VCU, Betsy Pittman of Special Collections and Archives; Cheryl Gonzales Yeaman of the Office of Development and Harold Nemuth, MD of the Department of Preventative Medicine, 1984 March 16, 1988 August 29, 1992 October 7 (Box-folder 1:29)
  - Weinburg, Jay, 1984 September 12, 1993 August 12 (Box-folder 1:30)
  - Windmueller, Fred, Husband, 1965 July 10, 1965 July 24 (Box-folder 1:31)
  - Windmueller, Evelyn, with photographs, circa 1966 (Box-folder 1:32)
  - Windmueller, Steven and Michelle, Son and Daughter in-law, 1990s (Box-folder 1:33)
  - Winters, Wendi, 1987 (Box-folder 1:34)
  - Unidentified Friend, in German, 1955, 1966 (Box-folder 1:35)
  - Miscellaneous Friends and Family with no last names given, 1980s, 1990s (Box-folder 1:36)
  - Bulletin Congregation Beth Ahaba, Generations, 1980 January, 1987 May, 1994 July (Box-folder 1:36)
  - Caricature of Otti, undated (Box-folder 1:37)
  - MCV and VCU Newsletter, 1991 December (Box-folder 1:38)
  - Miscellaneous, includes Otti Windmueller Business Card, circa 1993 (Box-folder 1:39)
  - Mitteilungsblatt Heimatverein Borghorst, 1987 (Box-folder 1:40)
  - Myers-Briggs Type Test, 1986 (Box-folder 1:41)
  - Poem to Neighbors Phil and Estelle by Otti Windmueller, 1982 February 28 (Box-folder 1:42)
  - Signed Photograph of Leontyne Price, circa 1980s (Box-folder 1:43)
  - Scholarship, 1989, 1990 (Box-folder 1:44)
  - Sigawanga theme song, undated (Box-folder 1:45)
  - VCU School of the Arts Fashion Show, 1982 April 30 (Box-folder 1:46)
  - Yiddish Language excerpt, undated (Box-folder 1:47)
- Photographs 1980s-1993 (Box 2)
  - Fashion Show, circa 1980s (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Forty years of service at VCU and scholarship, 1993 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Professor Emerita Ceremony, 1993 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Trip to Germany, 1993 July to August (Box-folder 2:4)
- News Clippings, undated, 1980s-1990s (Box 3)
  Items in this series are either full newspaper or partial newspapers that are oversized and not foldered.
  - News clippings, Richmond Times-Dispatch 1980s-1992 (Box 3:1)
  - Reform Judaism 1981 February (Box 3:2)
  - VCU Today, 1982 April 21 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - VCU Voice, 1984 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Miscellaneous News Clippings, undated (Box-folder 3:5)